Guide to the S.R. Slavson Papers 1905-1981 MC 141
New York University Archives
S.R. Slavson Papers
1905-1981
MC 141
New York University Archives
15.0 linear feet
S .R. Slavson was a prominent psychologist and leading figure in the development and study of group psychotherapy. These papers document the development of Slavson's career and offer a look into the nascent stages of group psychotherapy, particularly in the Group Therapy Department of the Jewish Board of Guardians, but also in various other social service agencies. The collection also contains considerable material relating to the founding of the American Group Psychotherapy Association, and personal materials which deal with Slavson's early interest in creative writing, socialism and labor activism.
Slavson, S. R., (Samuel Richard), 1891-
Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged chronologically and the remainder of the collection is arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 7 series:
I, Correspondence and Biographical Material.
II, Published and Unpublished Manuscripts.
III, Group Treatment Record and Case Histories.
IV, Organizations (unprocessed).
V, Miscellaneous (unprocessed).
VI, Video and Audio Recordings (unprocessed).
VII, Awards, Certificates and Honors (unprocessed).
Physical Access
Please note that this collection is stored offsite, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of correspondence; manuscripts; case histories and records; organizational materials, including Youth Consultation Service, Children's Village, World Federation of Mental Health, American Mental Health Foundation, and Brooklyn State Hospital; video and sound recordings; awards and certificates; notebooks; book reviews; clippings; and notes from approximately 1905 through 1978. Materials document Slavson's career and offer an interesting look into the early days of group psychotherapy in New York City. There is considerable material on the Group Therapy Department of the Jewish Board of Guardians, psychotherapy in social service agencies, founding of the American Group Psychotherapy Association, as well as personal biographical materials. Among the collection were the papers of William Weinstone, founder of the Communist Party of the United States of America. Some of the early writings found in Series II may have been created by Weinstone and not Slavson.
The collection has been divided into seven series.
Series I: Correspondence and Biographical Material, 1917-1978, includes: general correspondence to and from Slavson from 1930-1978. The correspondence concerns books and papers written by Slavson, letters to editors, requests for information from social service agencies from around the world and letters to and from family members and friends. Also included are invitations to lecture, lecture schedules and biographical material, including: newspaper and magazine clippings and speeches from his retirement dinner at the Jewish Board of Guardians.
Series II: Published and Unpublished Manuscripts, 1900s-1970s. Slavson wrote approximately 200 articles and 16 books. This series includes published and unpublished manuscripts, some typed and others handwritten. Since most of the material was not dated, it is arranged alphabetically by title or topic (when no title was available). A great many (possibly) unpublished and undated material is present, including early writings consisting of poetry, novels, essays and short stories. The series begins with several folders of numbered articles which were intended to be published together in one volume. Boxes 6 and 7 contain journals and books, in English and other languages.
Series III: Group Treatment Records and Case Histories, 1927-1963. This series deals with treatment records and case histories and is closed to researchers.
Series IV-VII contain reprints of articles, clippings, photographs and audio and video recordings (unprocessed).
Historical/Biographical Note
S.R. Slavson was a psychologist, teacher, writer, poet and labor activist born in the Ukraine on December 25, 1890. Slavson arrived in New York at age 13 after his family's escape from the pogroms in Russia. While struggling to support himself, Slavson sought to educate himself. In the process, he acquired an interest in poetry and literature, as well as a proclivity for science. After reading Rousseau's Emile, he began to embrace the ideals of socialism, and became a member of the Socialist Party in 1904. These political leanings brought him to the labor movement where he was instrumental in the formation of the Ladies Garment Workers Union.
Slavson attended evening school at the Cooper Union and graduated with a B.S. in Engineering. Subsequently, he studied briefly at Columbia Teachers College. After a number of positions in education, he gradually became immersed in the study of child psychology, which, coupled with his interest in social justice, led to Slavson's emergence as a pivotal figure in modern psychology and psychoanalysis. In 1934 Slavson was made director of Group Therapy at the Jewish Board of Guardians where he served until retiring in 1956. Besides his ceaseless work at developing innovative ways to deal with the psychological issues of urban youth, Slavson consulted frequently with numerous other mental health facilities during his tenure. From 1956-1968, he continued his work and shaped new theories on the treatment of delinquent adolescents and institutionalized psychotics. Until his death in 1981, he wrote prolifically, often lectured, and was frequently honored by his peers and colleagues.
Sources:
Slavson, S.R. "Beginnings." Voices: the art and science of psychotherapy. American Academy of Psychotherapists. Chicago. Spring, 1970.
Slavson, S.R. Biographical File. NYU Archives.
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection that contain patient names and case histories are closed (Series III). This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
The collection was transferred to the NYU Archives from Farleigh Dickinson University in December 1995. It was donated to FDU by Slavson's family in 1979.
American Group Psychotherapy Association.; American Mental Health Foundation.; Brooklyn State Hospital.; Children's Village (Dobbs Ferry, N.Y.).; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Jewish Board of Guardians.; Slavson, S. R., (Samuel Richard), 1891-; Weinstone, William W., (William Wolf), 1897-1985; World Federation of Mental Health. Congress. 1977. (University of British Columbia); Youth Consultation Service.; Audiotapes.; awards.; case histories.; Certificates.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Group psychotherapy.; Manuscripts (document genre).; Manuscripts for publication.; Notebooks; Notes.; phonograph records.; Photographs.; Psychotherapy |x Case Studies.; Psychotherapy |x Practice.; Psychotherapy |z New York (State) |z New York.; Psychotherapy.; Reviews (document genre).; speeches.; videotapes.
- Series I: Correspondence and Biographical Material, 1917-1978
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes general correspondence to and from Slavson from 1930-1978.Correspondence concerns books and papers written by him, letters to editors, requests for information from social service agencies worldwide and letters to and from family members and friends. Also included are invitations to lecture, lecture schedules and biographical material,including newspaper and magazine clippings and speeches from his retirement dinner at the Jewish Board of Guardians.
  - Correspondence, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    3 1142 04059378 5
  - Correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    3 1142 04059379 3
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with his children, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Carl Frankenstein, 1948-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence with archivist at Farleigh Dickenson University, 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Invitations to Speak, 1940-1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Invitations to Speak, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Invitations to Speak, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Biographical Materials, 1917-1933 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3 1142 04059380 1
  - Biographical Materials, 1946-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Materials, 1961-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Foreign Clinicians (Names and Addresses), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lecture Schedules, 1938-1952 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Testimonial Retirement Dinner (speeches, telegrams and invitations), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series II: Published and Unpublished Manuscripts, 1900s-1970s
  - Bibliographies, 1905-1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Complete Writings on Group Psychotherapy (Articles1-8), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Practice of Group Psychotherapy (Articles 9-39), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - History of Group Psychotherapy (Articles 40-45), undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Social Aspects (Articles 46-52), undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Case Histories (Articles 53-57), undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Adolescence and Deliquency (Articles 58-66), undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Various (Articles 67-85a), undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Activity Group Therapy (Possible Manuscript), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Anatomy of Education (Chapters 1-5), undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Anatomy of Education (Chapters 6-15), undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Articles (A-B), undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Child Psychotherapy, Draft #1, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Child Psychotherapy, Draft #2, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Child Psychotherapy (Draft #3), undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Classics in Psychiatry (Script for LP), 1954 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Conference Papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Creative Education, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - A Critique of Education and Modern Times, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    3 1142 04059381 9
  - Articles: C, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Danilo's Tales: Stories by SRS, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Articles: D, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Early Writings, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Early Writings, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Articles: E-F, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Give Yourself a Chance (Unpublished), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Glossary for Group Therapy, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Articles: G, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Articles: H-M, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, #1, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Writings #2, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Writings #3, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Writings #4, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Writings #5, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Writings #6, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Writings on Libido, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Writings on Club Work, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Moses, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Notes (In Folder Labeled: "Very Important"), undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Notes For an Article on Pre-school, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Notes For a Possible Book, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Notes For a Possible Book on Group Work, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Notes on Group Therapy, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Notes on Work at Brooklyn State Hospital, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Articles: N-P, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Papers On Group Psychotherapy, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    3 1142 04059382 7
  - Articles: P, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Articles: Q-S, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Remarks, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Reviews by SRS, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reviews of Slavson's Books #1, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Reviews of Slavson's Books #2, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Some Problems of Parenthood, Part I, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Some Problems of Parenthood, Part II, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Talks and Lectures, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Textbook Draft, Part I, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Textbook Draft, Part II, Chapters 9-12, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Textbook Draft, Part III, Chapters 13-14, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Textbook Draft, Part IV, Chapter 15, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Therapist and His Functions, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Thoughts on Life and Education, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Types of Psychotherapies and Their Clinical Applications, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Unbending the Human Twig, #1, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Unbending the Human Twig, #2, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Unbending the Human Twig, #3, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Unpublished Essays on Children, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Yeshiva University Seminar Notes, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Articles: T-Z, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Anais do Congresso Latino-Americano de Psicoterapia de Grupo, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    3 1142 04059383 5
  - Archives of Criminal Psychodynamics Vol. 1, No., 1955 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Einfuhrung in Die Gruppentherapie, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Einfuhrung in die Gruppentherapie von Kindern under Jugendlichen, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego I Gruppi per Genitori. L'orientamento centrato sul bambino, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - An Introduction to Group Therapy, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Nervous Child, Vol. 6, No. 4, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Proceedings of the Second International Congress of Group Psychotherapy. Zurich, Aug. 29-31, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Psicoterapia di Gruppo per Bambini, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Revista de Psiquiatria y psicologia medica de Europa y Americas Latinas., 1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Sozialpsychiatrie:Social Psychiatry, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - A Textbook in Analytic Group Psychotherapy, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Analytische Gruppenpsychotherapie Grundalangen und Praxis, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    3 1142 04059384 3
  - The Challenge for Group Psychotherapy Present and Future, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Child Centered Group Guidance of Parents, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Childhood Education, Vol. XV, No. 8, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Concise Handbook for Ward Personnel (Brooklyn State Hospital), 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Criteria for Selection and Rejection of Patients for Various Types of Group Psychotherapy, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Fields of Group Psychotherapy, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Further Observations on Group Psychotherapy with Adolescent Delinquent Boys in Residential Treatment, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Group, Vol. 1, No. 1 - Vol. 8, No. 3, 1939-1946 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Group Psychotherapy. Survey of 1948 Literature. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Group Therapy for Young Children, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Group Work: An Educational Factor in the Community, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Gruppen Psychotherapie, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Gruppenpsychotherapie mit Kindern Ein Arbeitsbuch, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - The Journal of Educational Sociology, V13, No. 4, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Mental Hygiene, Vol. XXXI, No. 3, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - The Nervous Child, Vol. 9, No. 2, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - The News-letter of the American Association of Psychiatric Social Workers,Vol. XII, No. 4, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - The Phenomenology and Dynamics of Silence in Psychotherapy Groups, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Preliminary Notes on the Relation of Psychodrama and Group Psychotherapy, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Proceedings of the Connecticut Conference on Group Work, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - The Psychiatric Quarterly Supplement Vol. 41, Part I, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Die Psychotherapie in Der Gegenwart, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Psychotherapie Analytique de Groupe, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Revue Francaise de Psychanalyse, Tome. XXII, No. 6, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Sandoz Psychiatric Spectator, Vol. VI, No. 61970, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Steps in Sensitizing Parents (Couples) in Groups Towards Schizophrenic Children, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Tratado de Psicoterapia Grupal Analitica, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Vita-Erg Therapy with Long-term Regressed Psychotic Women, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Series III: Group Treatment Records and Case Histories, 1927-1963 (Restricted)
- Series IV: Organizations, 1938-1968
  - American Group Psychotherapy Association (AGPA) History, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04225635 7
  - AGPA History (drafts), undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - AGPA Correspondence, 1949-1952 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - AGPA Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - AGPA (Various documents), 1956-1972 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - AGPA (Minutes and Reports), 1956 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - American Mental Health Foundation, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Group Psychotherapy Institute, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Group Psychotherapy Institute, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - International Committee on Group Psychotherapy, 1955-1957 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - International Committee on Group Psychotherapy, 1954-1955 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - International Journal of Group Psychotherapy (SRS correspondence with editors), 1958-1959 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - International Journal of Group Psychotherapy, 1951-1955 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Int'l Jnl of Gp. Psychotherapy (articles edited by SRS), undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Jewish Board of Guardians, 1938-1949 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Jewish Board of Guardians. Group Therapy: A Survey of Practices at the Jewish Board of Guardians., 1935-1941 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Jewish Board of Guardians (minutes & annual reports), 1947-1948 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Jewish Board of Guardians (employment inquiries), 1952-1954 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    barcode: 3 1142 04225636 5
  - Jewish Board of Guardians Group Therapy Dept., 1938-1950 (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Items, 1935-1969
  - World Federation for Mental Health, undated (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Activity Group Therapy (film script), 1949-1959 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Activity Group Therapy (film script), 1949-1959 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1930's-1950's (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Columbia University Press, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Congresses, 1954-1957 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Delinquency in the Great City, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - European Trip (includes a diary), 1957 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - European Trip (mostly correspondence), 1959 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1944-1948 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Papers (not by SRS), undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Reprints and clippings, 1957-1969 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Reprints and clippings, 1935-1967 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Reprints and clippings, 1935-1951 (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Series VI: LP's, Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1953 - 1972
  - Seminar at Arden House, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Two 33 rpm LP's. KUHF Recording. University of Houston Psychology Dept. Dr. Richard I.Evans, Associate Professor of Psychology, interviews SRS., undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04225637 3
  - Four 78 rpm LPs: Luncheon in honor of SRS at AGPA. January 1953. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Three 7 inch reel to reel audiotapes (Contents undetermined. Could be retirement dinner speeches.), undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Sony Videotape for helical scan video recorders (half inch video). AGPA #1 & AGPA #2. February 11, 1972 (Contents undetermined.) (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Awards, Certificates and Honors, 1953 -1975
  - Six 78 rpm LPs. Group Psychotherapy with Alcoholics., undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - The American Orthopsychiatric Association. Life Fellowship Certificate., 1971 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - NY Academy of Sciences. Certificate of Active Membership., 1958 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Eastern Group Psychotherapy Society. Wilfred C. Hulse Award., 1964 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - American Group Psychotherapy Association. Fellowship Certificate., 1953 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - American Group Psychotherapy Association. Certificate of Recognition., 1958 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Association for Improvement of Mental Health. Adolf Meyer Award., 1956 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - American Group Psychotherapy Association. 25th Anniversary Certificate., 1969 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Board of Guardians Educational Institute. Certificate., 1975 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - American Group Psychotherapy Association. Life Fellowship Certificate., 1971 (Box 15, Folder 9)